Let's talk about Kubernetes
scaling for cost savings and
maximal stability and resilience.
Today we have horizontal pod autoscaler,
vertical pod autoscaler, and much more.
This shows you why and how to go
beyond that I'm Joshua Fox, senior
cloud architect at DoiT, also a
Google developer expert, and I advise
customers on cost, resilience, and
much more as DoiT International.
So we at DoiT, besides advising
our customers, have a suite of
software for analyzing cost savings
opportunities and implementing them.
Perfect Scale is our product for
doing that, and this talk comes from
my experience in advising customers
about these topics and also from
our experience with Perfect Scale.
Although it's not about the product,
it's about the principles that you
can apply Cost savings in Kubernetes,
wonderful thing, but it is not
enough because there is a trade-off
between cost and operational risk.
After all, if you cut your resources
to a minimum, something might crash.
So you have to find the Pareto frontier.
That's the point at which making one
of these better will make the other
one worse if you push it too far.
So you have to choose where along the
frontier your solution comes out, what
is your trade-off between these two
metrics, but the goal is to push it
towards that frontier Auto-scaling is
the typical way to do this in Kubernetes.
That means that we automatically
add more nodes, remove nodes,
add more pods or remove pods.
And we'll be focusing mostly on
pods today, though not entirely.
Also, in addition to horizontally adding
more nodes and pods, we can vertically
expand the node or expand the pod.
And of course, when I say add or expand,
we also have to reduce if we're going
to achieve our goal of saving money.
Now, here are some of the steps that go
into pod scaling, and I'll explain why
the solutions we have today are ‑ right
sizing, that's the vertical tuning of CPU
or memory requests and limits for a pod.
Request means how much we ask for, limits
mean we don't ever want more than that.
Scaling is the horizontal,
adding or removing replicas of
the pods or adding nodes based
on demand and business signals.
And then consolidate.
Once we've decided how many pods we're
supposed to have and how large they should
be, we might find that some of our virtual
machine capacity, node capacity is wasted.
So we then pack the pods into the correct
number of nodes, leaving little or no
waste, and remove some of the nodes later
So this is great, but there are
some flaws and limitations with it.
One is signal granularity.
So for example, if we just
look at the average CPU, we
might miss some microbursts.
We might miss the fact that
CPU is maxed out, and that
slowed down the whole process.
And can't just look at average.
On the other hand, we don't
have too fine a granularity.
After all, perhaps this just lasted a
few milliseconds, and if we spin up more
computing power, it's a waste of money
since the worst we've done is slightly
delay response, increase latency.
So that's a trade-off.
I said CPU, the same
is true of memory, GPU.
Another limitation with the system
I described is a conflict between
horizontal and vertical autoscaling.
Let's say a horizontal autoscaler decides
to add pods, but now that's reduced
the need for any pod to grow larger.
On the other hand, the vertical
autoscaler at the exact same moment
decided to add more pod capacity, CPU
or memory, expand the size of each pod,
reducing the need to add more pods.
That's a conflict.
Some sort of waste is going
on here because any of these
processes, adding more pods,
expanding pods, does take some time
Eviction.
So if we increase the pod size,
then at least until recently, it
was necessary to shut down the old
small pod and spin up a large one.
Now, in Kubernetes, that's fine.
Kubernetes is built around stateless
workloads and an understanding that any
given component can crash at any moment.
That's a fact about the cloud.
It's a fact about any computing system.
So all that's okay, and yet in
reality, not everything is stateless.
We do have stateful sets for
databases, perhaps in-memory databases.
We have slow start workloads.
Perhaps the Java virtual machine
takes time to start up, and during
that time, the shutdown and the
startup is causing some disruption.
Cache sensitive workloads.
So logically, a cache makes no difference.
Either a value can be calculated
or it can be pulled from the cache.
But if a new pod is spun up,
then perhaps many values have
to be pulled from the cache,
and that changes the behavior.
So eviction itself means that resizing
is not the simple the simple change that
it appears to be Let's talk about other
potential issues with the system today.
Layered telemetry.
There are many ways to gather metrics.
Now, ultimately with telemetry, our goal
is to ask, is the workload under pressure?
Is the workload pressure
sustained or transient?
So if, for example we don't even want to
change anything if the workload pressure
might be going for just a very short time.
And will the change improve service health
or only change the dashboard number?
We're not here to make the metrics happy.
We're here to make the customers happy.
So let's talk about the different
types of telemetry that come together.
Starting from the infrastructure at
the very lowest level, and I'm going
to go into detail in a minute, going up
to the Kubernetes workflow in the pod.
Stepping beyond that to the Kubernetes
deployment, which is expressed
as a customer-facing application.
Going up a layer to
Kubernetes change and risk.
I spoke earlier that when we change a
value, that might itself cause disruption
during the transition, and we have
to calculate what is the real risk,
not just the measured impact, but the
probability of an even worse impact.
And then decision and actuation.
Ultimately, we have to decide
what to do, whether to scale up,
scale down, and then we need to
trigger a component that does that.
So in the infrastructure level, we're
measuring capacity and resource pressure.
So for example, to talk about the
node, very lowest layer, we're
measuring the CPU, the memory, and GPU.
For this, we have an NVIDIA
standard DCGM for scaling based
on streaming multiprocessor
utilization, memory bandwidth.
So these are all measured
on that infrastructure level
along with the container.
One step up, cAdvisor, which is an
open source standard from Google,
short for Container Advisor, might
for example track mult- microburst
latency on the container level.
So let's say that there's a page cache.
Memory is swapped in and out of page
cache, totally normal, and not really
an indication of a memory problem.
So that's at an infrastructure level.
Going up to the workload level, we
look at the Kubernetes configuration
that you typically write out in
YAML, and the lifecycle context of
how the pods spin up, spin down.
For example, we look at the requested
resources, how many replicas there
are, and whether any pods are pending.
So with that horizontal pod autoscaler,
it's not enough to say we added a pod.
We have to ask, is it ready yet?
So we don't Let's say we have
three pods, we go up to four.
One of those is not really ready.
We don't wanna spin up another pod because
we think that fourth pod is not real.
And Kubernetes state metrics is a
standard for pulling all this information
On the application level, we can ask
why is the workload under pressure?
Not just the fact that it is, but why.
So the Kubernetes can see the memory,
the CPU, but maybe the problem comes
from the fact that your Java app
is choking on garbage collection.
So this sort of thing is measured with
eBPF, a Linux standard for listening
to the kernel at a very low level,
listening to system calls, but in
a sandboxed way so that there's no
disruption of security or performance.
And
The JVM can use this as well.
The JVM is of course a separate
abstraction layer that can be plugged
in with the code agent to understand
heap allocation or garbage collection
pressure Example of application relevant
metrics we're measuring here are latency.
How long does that web request
take to be processed or queued up?
In an asynchronous application,
is the queue backing up?
Moving on to the next
layer, change and risk.
Is the action safe?
This has to be based on a long history.
Have certain actions like
scaling down caused crashes?
And here we have to track
the revision history.
What's happened in the past?
If we have a new revision, which
is an application code change, that
means something different from a new
revision which simply tweaks pod size.
An application revision could
involve new application pods or a new
pattern in using memory, for example.
SLOs and policy.
How much are you willing to tolerate?
For example, let's say that the
latency is worsened for one millisecond
for a time period of one second.
Do your customers suffer?
But not very much.
Is that worth it to you to save $100,000?
I just made up those figures, but
these are decisions you have to make.
Set them in your policy expressed
as SLOs service level goals
And now the highest level,
decision and actuation.
So here, your controller has to decide
what changes and how to apply them.
Has to calculate what to do, and
we're going to talk about unified
logic in greater detail later.
But ultimately, everything
has to come together.
Otherwise, you're either ignoring
some of the values or allowing
them to conflict with each other.
And then you actuate them with horizontal
pod, autoscaler, vertical, or with a
cluster autoscaler, which is on the node
level, and further with bin packing,
which I mentioned earlier, means
positioning the pods on the nodes to
use the node resources as effectively as
possible All these flow through, starting
with telemetry signals, diagnosing
what happened, dynamic, for example.
Making a decision, for
example, increasing pod size.
Actuating that, let's say with a
vertical pod autoscaler, for example.
And then guardrails that are always
inspecting the process and checking
that they're not making things worse.
So step one, mapping signal to decision.
For example, we decide based on
the container memory behavior to
change the memory request limits.
Next level, configuring the HPA.
And so we look at the history of scale
up and scale down to the A, and add
to our scaling context awareness.
For example, we notice that each decision
has taken five seconds to fully implement.
So on that level, we're not going to make
any hasty decisions within that window.
Next, mapping signal to decision.
We look at the revision
timeline, distinguish changes
in application code from changes
that were there for optimization.
And these can have very
different consequences.
Next mapping, GPU and JVM signals.
Here we notice the JVM, for example, is
behaving a certain way, and therefore
there's a bottleneck on the JVM level.
Different from the other levels, we
have to decide what to do for that.
And finally, risk indicators.
Most of my customers are very concerned
with crashes, of course they are, and
so typically they prioritize resilience
over savings, although as I mentioned
earlier, everything's a trade-off.
Would you allow one second of downtime
a year to save a million dollars?
These decisions are yours
Now earlier I spoke about
the risks of pod resizing.
You take the pod down, you
bring up a larger pod, and then
there is some downtime perhaps.
Unless you leave an
extra buffer, of course.
But there is a new feature in
Kubernetes, stable from version 1.35,
available even earlier in pre-release
form, which is in-place pod resizing.
Then you can tell the pod
that it's allowed to have more
memory without shutting it down.
So it's good for stateful workloads and
even for stateless ones, for example,
with cold starts I mentioned the
importance of a unified scaling logic.
This is to avoid conflict.
You want to actuate the correct
amount of Kubernetes resources,
taking into account a lot of different
metrics, telemetry, and a lot for-
lot of different ways to actuate.
Horizontal versus
vertical, pause versus go.
All these autoscalers are working
at the same time, and as I
mentioned, potentially conflicting.
It's not just conflicts.
You might want to decide which is the best
of those to put into practice to actuate.
So for this, a custom controller can
be implemented, for example, with
Akka, has to come together, take
all these telemetries and balance
the different signals, balance the
different actuation possibilities
and risks, and decide what to do.
This is unlike typical situation where
multiple autoscalers kick in Here's
how the logical unification works.
It aggregates the many different
signals, many different telemetries
that I mentioned to you.
It arbitrates between the axes.
Should we be doing a node autoscaler?
Should we be doing horizontal, vertical?
And then once it's done
that, it's enabled cool down.
That means we have an overheated
system that is running beyond
CPU available, for example.
We give it a certain
amount of time to resolve.
We give it time to catch up with
processes that might have been
slowed and latency was slowed, even
in a fully synchronous application.
If it slows down, it might have to
wait for the application to cool down
and calculate what it was supposed to.
And finally, reconciliation.
That means look again at the telemetry
and check that it works, and that
in fact, the system has responded.
In all cases, not merely being aware
of CPU, memory, GPU, but also impact.
Is it making things slow down or crash?
Once we've implemented this unified
logic, optimizations, instead of
conflicting, can feed into each other.
For example, more accurate pod
requests, whether in terms of the
number of pods or their size, leads
to more optimal bin packing and
then fewer underutilized nodes.
Now the autoscaler can consolidate
and shut down unneeded resources.
In conclusion, optimization
is your policy decision.
How much latency is worth $100,000 to you?
Today, these decisions are often
made intuitively by guessing,
by panicking when things crash.
Do you really know how much
downtime, how much latency will be
caused by reducing your resources?
Or conversely, how much it will
cost you to increase resources and
allow some . This is a trade-off
that has to be monitored and
calculated in an optimal way.
Unifying the logic for different types of
metrics and scaling, and so stop scaling
based on utilization of CPU or memory.
Start scaling based on a holistic view
of cost, service health, and risk.
I'll be very glad to get your questions.
This is an online conference, so
you can either catch me in one of
the forums and conversation rooms
or email me, joshua@nethit.com